<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Joao Junior</title>
    <link>https://joaojunior.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Joao Junior</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 10:29:19 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://joaojunior.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Why Is Atomicity Not Enough?</title>
      <link>https://joaojunior.org/posts/why-is-atomicity-not-enough/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 10:29:19 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</author>
      <guid>https://joaojunior.org/posts/why-is-atomicity-not-enough/</guid>
      <description>When we study transactions in relational databases, one of the first things we learn are the guarantees that a transaction must provide. ACID(Atomicity, Consistency, Isolation, Durability) are the properties that we desire. Here, I will discuss the Isolation level in more detail and show that atomicity alone is not enough when handling concurrency.
One classic example of the importance of atomicity is moving money between accounts. So, imagine that we have two accounts and we would like to transfer the total amount from one account to another one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quicksort</title>
      <link>https://joaojunior.org/posts/quicksort/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2021 15:54:55 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</author>
      <guid>https://joaojunior.org/posts/quicksort/</guid>
      <description>The Quicksort algorithm was created by Tony Hoare in 1961 and it is a very powerful algorithm to sort an array in memory until today. Here, I will describe the Quicksort algorithm, show an implementation in Python, and analyze the time complexity of this algorithm in the worst and best scenarios.
The idea behind the Quicksort is so simple: to sort an array \(V\) of \(n\) elements, it is easier to sort smaller sub-arrays of \(V\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing Data-Intensive Applications: Review</title>
      <link>https://joaojunior.org/posts/designing-data-intensive-applications-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2021 10:02:04 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</author>
      <guid>https://joaojunior.org/posts/designing-data-intensive-applications-review/</guid>
      <description>Disclaimer: Don&amp;rsquo;t read this review, go ahead and read the book, it will be much better for you. The only reason that I wrote this is for my future reference.
First of all, I love to read books and I do not believe that a review should influence someone to read or not a book. However, as a researcher, one of the most important things that I learned during my years at the university was the importance to write a review of papers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chrome with selenium, python and docker</title>
      <link>https://joaojunior.org/posts/my-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2019 09:15:55 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</author>
      <guid>https://joaojunior.org/posts/my-first-post/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes, when I execute the Chrome inside a docker container I receive the error below:
selenium.common.exceptions.WebDriverException: Message: unknown error: Chrome failed to start: crashed
It is caused because Chrome uses the /dev/shm to share memory and the docker, by default, set 64MB for this partition.
Here, I will describe how to reproduce this error and how to resolve it.
How to reproduce To reproduce this error, we need to create a docker image with chrome and python.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Paragraphs</title>
      <link>https://joaojunior.org/posts/identify-paragraphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2017 17:00:19 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</author>
      <guid>https://joaojunior.org/posts/identify-paragraphs/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m learning computer vision and I&amp;rsquo;m using the Opencv and Python to write algorithms in this field of computer science. This field is very interesting because it involves computer science and math and also, it is necessary to have good ideas to solve problems.
Here, I will show my first algorithm in computer vision. It is to identifies paragraphs in a text image. It consider that the image have a white background and that the characters have a black color.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources in Operational Research</title>
      <link>https://joaojunior.org/posts/my-second-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2017 09:42:04 -0400</pubDate>
      <author>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</author>
      <guid>https://joaojunior.org/posts/my-second-post/</guid>
      <description>I wrote a list of operational research resource which contains many name of books, events, groups, solvers and teachers. I publish this list here. It is a github&amp;rsquo;s repository and you can help to update :-)
I wrote it based on the list, wrote by Avelino, about resources for go programming language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Callbacks in Cplex</title>
      <link>https://joaojunior.org/posts/callbacks-in-cplex/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2017 16:48:25 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</author>
      <guid>https://joaojunior.org/posts/callbacks-in-cplex/</guid>
      <description>Callbacks in Cplex I used LazyConstraintCallback to implement a Branch and Cut algorithm with CPLEX, but when I implemented and run this algorithm, it was very slow if I compare it with its version that doesn&amp;rsquo;t use callbacks in Cplex. The reason is because ControlCallback(LazyConstraintCallback is a ControlCallback) switch Cplex to sequential mode by default and turn off dynamic search. I wrote this post, because I didn&amp;rsquo;t find this information in Cplex’s documentation, I only found it in this technical forum.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>https://joaojunior.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</author>
      <guid>https://joaojunior.org/about/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m from Belo Horizonte - MG, Brazil and I already lived in United States, France, Malta and Canada.
I have been using computers since 1994 when my father gave me my first 486DX2 66MHz with 16MB of memory and a 2.1GB hard disk. On this computer, I started using MS-DOS as an operating system. After I used Windows Windows 3.11, Windows 95, Windows 98, and many other Windows operation system. About 1999/2000 I knew GNU/Linux and I started to use it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MCS</title>
      <link>https://joaojunior.org/mcs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</author>
      <guid>https://joaojunior.org/mcs/</guid>
      <description>I have a Master Degree in Computer Science (MCS) at Departamento de Ciência da Computação (DCC), Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais (UFMG). During my MCS, I have worked with two interesting NP-Hard optimization problems. I studied, the Robust Shortest Path Problem (RSP) and the Tree Hub Location problem (THLP). The former relies on a Shortest Path problem where uncertainties are considered over the arc costs. The latter is a network design problem where one looks to locate hubs in a tree backbone in order to reduce the routing total costs.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
