<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Python on Joao Junior</title>
    <link>https://joaojunior.org/tags/python/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Python on Joao Junior</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 12:40:06 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://joaojunior.org/tags/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Is CPython Faster Without the Global Interpreter Lock(GIL)?</title>
      <link>https://joaojunior.org/posts/is-cpython-faster-without-the-global-interpreter-lock-gil/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 12:40:06 -0400</pubDate><author>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</author>
      <guid>https://joaojunior.org/posts/is-cpython-faster-without-the-global-interpreter-lock-gil/</guid>
      <description>The Global interpreter lock(GIL) is a mechanism in CPython implementation to ensure only one thread is running at a time. This means that even if we use threads to try to speed up our programs&amp;rsquo; runtime, this will not work because, in the end, the interpreter will block that two or more threads will be executed in parallel.&#xA;As the name suggests, the GIL is a locker that a thread gets when it starts and releases at some moment.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chrome with selenium, python and docker</title>
      <link>https://joaojunior.org/posts/my-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2019 09:15:55 -0400</pubDate><author>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</author>
      <guid>https://joaojunior.org/posts/my-first-post/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes, when I execute the Chrome inside a docker container I receive the error below:&#xA;selenium.common.exceptions.WebDriverException: Message: unknown error: Chrome failed to start: crashed&#xA;It is caused because Chrome uses the /dev/shm to share memory and the docker, by default, set 64MB for this partition.&#xA;Here, I will describe how to reproduce this error and how to resolve it.&#xA;How to reproduce To reproduce this error, we need to create a docker image with chrome and python.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Paragraphs</title>
      <link>https://joaojunior.org/posts/identify-paragraphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2017 17:00:19 -0500</pubDate><author>blog@joaojunior.org (Joao Junior)</author>
      <guid>https://joaojunior.org/posts/identify-paragraphs/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m learning computer vision and I&amp;rsquo;m using the Opencv and Python to write algorithms in this field of computer science. This field is very interesting because it involves computer science and math and also, it is necessary to have good ideas to solve problems.&#xA;Here, I will show my first algorithm in computer vision. It is to identifies paragraphs in a text image. It consider that the image have a white background and that the characters have a black color.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
